Guide to the Fifth Avenue Coach Company Collection 1895-1962 PR 18
New-York Historical Society
Fifth Avenue Coach Company collection
1895-1962
New-York Historical Society
Fifth Avenue Coach Company
PR 18
6.67 Linear feet (473 mounted photographs, 309 unmounted prints of various sizes including cyanotypes, and 3 albums of photos, clippings and ephemera)
The Fifth Avenue Coach Collection of photographs dates from 1895 through 1962. The photos document the company's buses, bus operations, bus construction, bus repair and maintenance, bus stops and routes, and facilities. Views include work areas, as well as leisure areas for employees, and special events such as public service projects. Photos also show street scenes of the city. The albums contain clippings and other items documenting the company and its public relations.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from the Metropolitan Transit Authority in 1981.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in ten series:
Series I: Buses and Automotive Parts
Series II: Employee Photographs
Series III: Company Facilities
Series IV: Street Scenes
Series V: Instructional Images
Series VI: War Relief Effort
Series VII: Diagrams and Charts
Series VIII: Publicity Mock-ups
Series IX: Loose Photographs
Series X: Albums and Scrapbooks
Historical Note
The Fifth Avenue Coach Company, incorporated in 1896, was a horse-drawn omnibus line originally founded in 1885 as the Fifth Avenue Transportation Company (Ltd.) to discourage the laying of trolley tracks on the fashionable two-way thoroughfare. Battery operated vehicles were quickly abandoned after their introduction in 1900 as a result of their expense and inefficiency. Horse-drawn London-type omnibuses continued to be used until 1907, when they were replaced by gasoline-driven motor coaches with French engines and London chassis. The company began producing their own motor coaches in 1914 and became well known for their double-decker models.
The Fifth Avenue Coach Company became a subsidiary of the Third Avenue Railway Company in 1898 and the New York Transportation Company in 1899, gaining its independence in 1912. In 1924 it became a subsidiary of the Omnibus Corporation, which controlled the bus systems in New York and Chicago. In 1954, after acquiring the Hertz car rental business, the Omnibus Corporation sold the assets of the Fifth Avenue Coach Company to the New York City Omnibus Corporation, which was renamed Fifth Avenue Coach Lines in 1956. After a strike in 1962, the company's bus operations were taken over by the city.
Related Materials
Also housed in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections, the Subway Construction Photograph Collection and the Norvin H. Green Collection of Elevated Railways document alternative modes of public transportation in New York City in the first decades of the 20th century.
Scope and Contents
The Fifth Avenue Coach Company Collection documents the Manhattan company's buses, facilities, operations, and employees. Though the collection spans the years of the company's existence (1896-1954), most of the 473 mounted photographs date from 1915 through 1928. The photographs were commissioned by the company for advertising and public relations purposes, as well as for use in employee training. The mounted photographs were originally numbered consecutively and arranged in numerical order, with numerous gaps in the sequence.
Buses -- Design and construction.; Buses -- Maintenance and repair.; Buses -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bus lines -- New York (State) -- New York.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; New York (N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Cyanotypes; Photograph albums.; Photographic prints.; Scrapbooks.; Fifth Avenue Coach Company; Fifth Avenue Transportation Company; New York City Omnibus Corporation; New York Transportation Company
- Series I: Buses and Automotive Parts, 1915-1928
  Scope and Contents
  Series I houses photographs of the earliest coaches, including the horse-drawn omnibuses, in addition to all of the various models produced through the late 1920s. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by bus type or numerically by bus number when the type is not specified. Within each type, the items are arranged in the following order: exterior, interior, chassis and axles, and engine and parts. Interior bus views often show passengers, as well as the advertisements lining the upper walls. The series ends with miscellaneous and unidentified vehicles and automotive parts, arranged alphabetically.
  Views of type J include photographs of buses produced for the Grand Rapids Railways, the Capitol Traction Company (Washington, DC), the Milwaukee Electric Railway Company, and the Kansas Electric Power Company. Views of type 7J include buses manufactured for Detroit and for the Toronto Transportation Commission, and views of type L include a coach manufactured for Baltimore. Bus 701 is shown in both New York and Chicago, with a repainted exterior. The exterior of bus 914, a cooperative project of the New York Automobile Club and the Board of Education, is covered with signs exhorting safety, such as "Hurry leads to worry," and "Why take chances? Odds are against you."
  Views of miscellaneous buses include four images of an upper deck containing several couples evidently posed in romantic poses. According to a 1954 New York Times article, these so-called "spooners" favored the open-air upper decks in use from 1907 to 1936. As a result, certain strait-laced riders led a campaign against the open-air coaches as "instruments of evil." At around the same time these photographs were taken, John A. Ritchie, the head of the Fifth Avenue Coach Company in the 1920's, wrote a letter defending open-air spooning.
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by bus type or numerically by bus number when the type is not specified. Within each type, the items are arranged in the following order: exterior, interior, chassis and axles, and engine and parts.
  - [Early miscellaneous coaches], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Type A, Exterior, 1921 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Type A, Interior, 1921 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Type A, Chassis and axles, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Type A, Chassis and axles, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Type A, Engine and parts, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Type 2A, Exterior, 1922-1923 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Type 2A, Interior, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Type 2A, Chassis and axles, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Type 2A, Chassis and axles, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Type 2A, Chassis and axles, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Type 3A, Transmission, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Type 4A, Engine, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Type C, Chassis, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Type D, Exterior and accident views, 1916 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - Type D, Wheel, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Type E, Exterior, 1915 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Type E, Interior, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - Type G, Exterior and accident view, 1917 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  - Type G, Axle, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
  - Type G, Engine and parts, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
  - Type H, Exterior and accident view, 1915-1916 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
  - Type H, Interior, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
  - Type J, Exterior, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
  - Type J, Exterior, 1921 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
  - Type J, Exterior, 1923 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
  - Type J, Interior, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
  - Type J, Interior, 1923 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
  - Type J, Chassis, 1923 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
  - Type J, Engine and parts, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
  - Type 7J, Exterior, 1921 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
  - Type 7J, Exterior, 1922 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
  - Type 7J, Interior, 1921 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
  - Type 7J, Chassis, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
  - Type 8J, Exterior, 1922 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
  - Type 8J, Interior, 1922 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
  - Type 8J, Chassis, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
  - Type L, Exterior, 1919-1924 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 28)
  - Type L, Exterior, 1919-1924 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 29)
  - Type L, Exterior, 1919-1924 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 30)
  - Type L, Exterior, 1919-1924 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 31)
  - Type L, Chassis and axles, 1922-1923 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 32)
  - Type L, Chassis and axles, 1922-1923 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 33)
  - Type L, Chassis and axles, 1922-1923 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 34)
  - Type L, Chassis and axles, 1922-1923 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 35)
  - Type L, Engine and parts, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 36)
  - Type 2L, Exterior, 1923-1924 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 37)
  - Type 2L, Interior, 1923 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 37)
  - Type 2L, Chassis, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 38)
  - Type N, Exterior, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 39)
  - Type N, Engine, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 39)
  - Type R, Engine, 1923 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 40)
  - Bus 241, Exterior, 1917-1918 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 41)
  - Bus 241, Interior, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 41)
  - Bus 506, Exterior, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 42)
  - Bus 512, Exterior, 1919 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 42)
  - Bus 517, Exterior, 1919 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 42)
  - Bus 701, Exterior, 1917 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 43)
  - Bus 701, Exterior, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 44)
  - Bus 701, Interior, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 45)
  - Bus 701, Chassis, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 45)
  - Bus 808, Interior, 1922 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 46)
  - Bus 913, Exterior (first coach with pneumatic tires), undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 47)
  - Bus 914, Exterior [Safety signs], 1928 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Buses, [Couples on upper deck], undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous Buses, Unidentified, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous Vehicles, Sand car, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous Vehicles, Snow plows, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous Vehicles, Unidentified, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous Vehicles, Miscellaneous Automotive Parts, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous Vehicles, Miscellaneous Automotive Parts, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous Vehicles, Miscellaneous Automotive Parts, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous Vehicles, Unidentified Automotive Parts, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 53)
- Series II: Employee Photographs, 1917-1923
  Series II is divided into four subseries. The subseries "Activities" contains the menu for the testimonial dinner honoring company executive Captain G. A. Green, who went off to war in his native England in 1917. Also present is a photograph of a staff Baby Contest (1922) in the office of Dr. C. Sangfree, the staff doctor. There are of portraits of Captain Green and Dr. Sangfree, as well as the managerial staff at weekly meetings in Captain Green's office. In addition, photographs of the drivers' and conductors' winter and spring uniforms (1921-1923) have survived.
  Series II is divided into the following subseries: Activities, Portraits, Uniforms, and Prizes and Awards.
  - Subseries I: Activities
    - Menu: testimonial dinner to Mr. G. A. Green, Engineers' Club, 1917 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 54)
    - Baby Contest, 1922 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 54)
    - Circus Day, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 54)
  - Subseries II: Portraits
    - Capt. G. A. Green, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 55)
    - Staff- weekly meeting, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 55)
    - Dr. C. Sangfree, undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 55)
  - Subseries III: Uniforms
    - Uniforms, 1921-1923 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 56)
  - Subseries IV: Prizes and Awards
    - Prizes and Awards, 1921 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 57)
- Series III: Company Facilities
  Series III consists of images of the employees at work and at leisure in the various buildings in use by the company. Photographs are arranged numerically by street number and alphabetically by place name, and thereunder alphabetically by caption. The series ends with unidentified locations. The work and recreation areas of two facilities are exceptionally well documented: the company headquarters on 102nd Street and the second garage on 132nd Street. Work scenes include views of the offices, assembly floor, machine shop, and repair pits. Scenes of recreation and leisure, which emphasize the benefits and amenities provided to employees by the company, include views of the barbershop, restaurant, tailor shop, and reading room.
  Series III is arranged numerically by street number and alphabetically by place name, and thereunder alphabetically by caption.
  - 39th St. Employment Bureau, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 58)
  - 88th St. Garage, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 58)
  - 102nd St. Building [Main Headquarters], undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 59)
  - 102nd St. Building [Main Headquarters], undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 60)
  - 102nd St. Building [Main Headquarters], undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 61)
  - 102nd St. Building [Main Headquarters], undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 62)
  - 102nd St. Building [Main Headquarters], undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 63)
  - 110th St. and 5th Ave.: Waiting Room, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 64)
  - 130th St. Building: Employee's Club Room, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 64)
  - 132nd St. Building [No. 2 Garage], undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 65)
  - 132nd St. Building [No. 2 Garage], undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 66)
  - 133rd St. Garage- Excavation, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 67)
  - 144th St. Garage, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 67)
  - Penn Station- Starter's Booth, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 67)
  - Washington Square- Drivers' Room, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 67)
  - Unidentified Location, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 68)
- Series IV: Street Scenes, 1898-1923
  Series IV contains views of Manhattan dating primarily from the 1910s and 1920s, arranged numerically by street and avenue, and alphabetically by place name, according to the first-named element in the caption provided by the company. Three 1899 photographs document the construction of the Third Avenue Railway on upper Broadway. Three undated images from the 1910s offer views of Washington Square Park, the lower terminus of the Fifth Avenue line. Two photographs, also undated, show an Easter Parade along Fifth Avenue. A series of nine photographs taken the morning of 2 December 1915 depicts various Manhattan intersections from 14th Street to Times Square. Nine images dated 29 July 1921 show excavations underway along Fifth Avenue from 14th Street to 86th Street.
  Series IV is arranged numerically by street and avenue, and alphabetically by place name, according to the first-named element in the caption provided by the company.
  - 14th St. and Broadway, 1915, undated (Offsite-box 11, Folder 69)
  - 14th St. and 5th Ave., 1921 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 69)
  - 17th St. and Broadway, 1915 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 69)
  - 26th St. and 7th Ave., 1915 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 69)
  - 38th St. and 5th Ave., 1921 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 70)
  - 40th St. and Broadway, 1915 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 70)
  - 50th St. and 5th Ave., 1921 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 70)
  - 56th St. and 5th Ave., 1921 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 70)
  - 71st St. and 5th Ave., 1921 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 71)
  - 86th St. and 5th Ave., 1921 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 71)
  - 135th St. Stanchions, 1915 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 71)
  - 155th St. Stand, 1915 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 71)
  - 5th Ave. and 40th St., 1923 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 72)
  - 5th Ave. and 42nd St., undated (Offsite-box 11, Folder 72)
  - 5th Ave.: Easter Parade, undated (Offsite-box 11, Folder 72)
  - 7th Ave. and 25th St., 1915 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 73)
  - 7th Ave. and 35th St., 1915 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 73)
  - 7th Ave. and 41st St., 1915 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 73)
  - Broadway and 87th St., 1899 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 73)
  - Broadway and 116th St., 1899 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 73)
  - Broadway and 123rd St., 1899 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 73)
  - [Grant's Tomb], 1921 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 74)
  - Washington Square, 1921 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 74)
- Series V: Instructional Images, 1923
  Series V is divided into two subseries. Within each subseries, items are arranged alphabetically by caption. The first subseries contains images of employees adjusting, installing, operating, or assembling various vehicles and automotive parts. The second is a series of staged, didactic photographs depicting correct and incorrect practices for drivers and conductors. Examples of improper behaviors include smoking, reading the newspaper, miscalculating distances, stopping short, and leaving the bus unprotected. Images of model conduct show the proper way to make turns, usher passengers to the upper deck, and warn passengers before going under elevated structures.
  Series V is divided into two subseries: Repairs and Installations and Examples for Drivers and Conductors. Within each subseries, items are arranged alphabetically by caption.
  - Subseries I: Repairs and Installations
    - Repairs and Installations, undated (Offsite-box 12, Folder 75)
    - Repairs and Installations, 1923 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 76)
  - Subseries II: Examples for Drivers and Conductors
    - Examples for Drivers and Conductors, undated (Offsite-box 12, Folder 77)
    - Examples for Drivers and Conductors, undated (Offsite-box 12, Folder 78)
- Series VI: War Relief Effort, 1917
  Housed in Series VI are images related to the company's public relations endeavors during World War I. Present are photographs of the buses loaned to the American Red Cross in 1917, and to the Scotch Kilties for a recruiting tour that same year. One photograph depicts volunteers from the Woman's Motor Corps of America decorating the exterior of a bus, while another shows the same bus at the Fourth Liberty Loan Demonstration.
  - Buses Loaned to American Red Cross, 1917 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 79)
  - Red Cross Ambulance, undated (Offsite-box 12, Folder 79)
  - Scotch Kilties on Recruiting Tour, 1917 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 79)
  - War Work Outings for Soldiers, undated (Offsite-box 12, Folder 79)
  - Woman's Motor Corps of America, undated (Offsite-box 12, Folder 79)
- Series VII: Diagrams and Charts
  Series VII contains the following subseries: Types J and L, Graphs, and Miscellaneous. The images in the first subseries are photographs of sectional diagrams of types J and L coaches and schematic drawings of their component parts. The curves plotted along the graphs in the second subseries record such variables as the speed, engine performance, and acceleration of various types of coaches.
  Series VII contains the following subseries: Types J and L, Graphs, and Miscellaneous.
  - Subseries I: Types J and L
    - Types J and L, undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 80)
    - Types J and L, undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 81)
  - Subseries II: Graphs
    - Graphs, undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 82)
  - Subseries III: Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 83)
- Series VIII: Publicity Mock-ups
  - Mock-ups with printer's instructions, undated (Offsite-box 13, Folder 84)
- Series IX: Loose Photographs, 1897-1962
  Series IX is divided into six subseries. Within each subseries, the items are arranged in an approximate chronological fashion. The cyanotypes primarily document the 146th Street station house and the 9th Avenue and 54th Street car house from 1897 to 1910. The small format bus views contain some replicas of the mounted images, as well as several supplementary views from the 1920s, including seven additional photographs of Bus 914 in front of City Hall on 23 December 1926. Later views from the 1930s onward include the buses of the Fifth Avenue Coach Lines. The earliest 8 x 10 bus views duplicate several of the mounted images, though the bulk of the images depict coaches from the 1930s through the 1960s. Many of the photographs from the 1930s and 40s represent the buses of the Madison Avenue Coach Lines, the Eighth Avenue Coach Lines, the Chicago Motor Coach Lines, and the New York City Omnibus Corporation, all under common control by 1936. The latest photographs from the 1960s depict coaches from the Manhattan and Bronx Surface Transit Operating Authority, the entity that took control of the Fifth Avenue Coach Lines and its affiliates in 1962. Photographs of employees include two 1946 portraits of Operator Norman Peer, Badge 841, and two 1950s group snapshots of employees in the new locker room. Other views from the 1950s and 60s consist of executives giving speeches, attending at a ribbon-cutting ceremony, and celebrating at a banquet.
  Series IX is divided into the following subseries: Cyanotypes, Bus Views (small format), Bus Views (8 x 10), Street Scenes, Employees, and Miscellaneous. Within each subseries, the items are arranged in an approximate chronological fashion.
  - Subseries I: Cyanotypes, 1897-1910
    - 146th St. Station, 1897-1909 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 85)
    - 9th Ave. and 54th St. car house, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 85)
    - Loft Building, 22nd St. and Ave. A., on verso: 15th St. west of Ave. B, 1908 -1909 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 85)
  - Subseries II: Bus Views (small format)
    - Bus Views (small format), 1926-1960 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 86)
  - Subseries III: Bus Views (8x10)
    - Bus Views (8x10), 1915-1962 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 87)
    - Bus Views (8x10), 1915-1962 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 88)
    - Bus Views (8x10), 1915-1962 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 89)
  - Subseries IV: Street Scenes
    - Street Scenes, 1936-1959 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 90)
  - Subseries V: Employees
    - Employees, 1946 1953 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 91)
  - Subseries VI: Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous, 1939-1952 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 92)
- Series X: Albums and Scrapbooks
  Series X, Albums and Scrapbooks, shows the ways in which this photographic archive was used for public relations and advertising purposes by the Fifth Avenue Coach Company in the 1910s and 20s. The large scrapbook contains items dated from 1911 to 1922 arranged with an internal alphabetical index supplied by its creator. It houses a variety of types of materials, including maps, route guides, fare schedules, passes, advertisements, advertising contracts, announcements, employee bulletins, public pamphlets, annual reports, letters to stockholders, and invitations to company events. It also contains the March 1917 and January-February 1922 issues of Bus Lines, the in-house newsletter published by the company for its employees, and the 1917 booklet Motor Bus Relief for New York's Transit Needs, which explained and supported the company's application to the city for new routes. Pamphlets for employees promoting courtesy, safety, and civility complement the contemporary photographs of the type A buses with civility signs in Series I and Series IV.
  The March 1917 issue of Bus Lines reproduces an image from Series V, "Cutting Rubber from Tires," to illustrate an article entitled "Paddy's Scheme and the Lesson it Teaches," about an employee's cost-saving suggestion to remove and sell the rubber from old tires. An October 1917 advertisement in British Empire Rally contains the image of the Scotch Kilties' recruiting tour, and a company postcard pictures the bus camouflaged by the Women's War Work Effort.